# CHRIS WILSON

Data journalist and newsroom interactive web developer

Washington, D.C. | christopher.e.wilson@gmail.com | (434) 242-9728

#### **O**VERVIEW

I'm a data journalist with 15 years of professional experience as both a reporter and a computer programmer. My specialty is researching and producing interactive graphics based on large datasets. I typically execute every stage of a project, from collecting the data, composing the statistical code to analyze it, conducting interviews based on the findings, writing an accompanying article, and developing user-friendly, interactive visualizations to make the data come alive. I am the author of O'Reilly's (now somewhat-dated) manual on RaphaelJS.

### TECHNICAL SKILLS

My strongest languages are JavaScript (ES6 and backward compliance), Node.js, Python, R and Mathematica. I'm well-versed in all modern JavaScript visualization libraries, such as D3.js, Three.js and Canvas, as well as the JavaScript development pipeline for using tools like Webkit to optimize code. On the database side, I typically use MonogDB or MySQL but have experience in several others.

### WORK EXPERIENCE

TIME Magazine, Aug. 2013 - present

Director of Data Journalism

- Have developed over 400 editorial interactives and data-driven reporting projects.
- Founder and lead developer of <u>TIME Labs</u>, **winner of the 2015 Eppy** for <u>Best Use of Data/Infographics with 1 million unique monthly visitors and over.</u>
- Have written the most-read article on Time.com for five of 8 years.

Yahoo News, Jan. 2012 - August 2013

Editor, Columnist

• Authored over 50 news interactives and wrote a weekly data-driven column.

Slate Magazine, Dec. 2007 - Nov. 2011

Senior Editor, Director of Slate Labs

• Wrote over 100 articles on technology, politics, and culture, including an <u>expose</u> on how Saddam Hussein was captured using social network theory.

- Developed several dozen multimedia features, such as maps, reader contests, and data visualizations.
- Winner of the <u>2010 Media Vanguard Award</u> for Best New Web-Publishing Idea Factory

#### U.S. News & World Report, Jan. 2007 - Dec. 2007

 Founded the News Desk blog and wrote several dozen articles as a reporter on the National Desk

#### Congressional Quarterly, Jan. 2006 - Dec. 2006

• Developed visualizations of Congressional and industry data.

#### Washingtonian Magazine, Sept. 2005 - July 2007

• Wrote longform science-related features for the magazine.

#### **EDUCATION**

University of Virginia (Charlottesville, Va.) 2001-2005

B.A., English; Concentration in physics; GPA: 3.59 (total), 3.80 (major)

Echols Scholar (Honors program for top 8.5% of Arts & Sciences students)

Standford Machine Learning Class (advanced track)

# Miscellaneous

Cofounder of <u>AnalyzeWords.com</u>, a site that uses natural language processing to determine your personality on Twitter.

Short story "The Dry Season" nominated for the Pushcart Prize.